<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us"><generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.96.0">Hugo</generator><title type="html">crypto on Mero's Blog</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/tags/crypto/"/><link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://blog.merovius.de/tags/crypto/atom.xml"/><updated>2022-04-06T10:31:35+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.merovius.de/tags/crypto/</id><author><name>Axel Wagner</name></author><entry><title type="html">Using roughtime as a "cryptographic notary"</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2018-10-10-using-roughtime-as-a-cryptographic-notary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2018/10/18/using-roughtime-as-a-cryptographic-notary.html</id><published>2018-10-10T23:22:40+00:00</published><updated>2018-10-10T23:22:40+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>tl;dr: Roughtime can be (ab)used for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trusted_timestamping#Trusted_(digital)_timestamping">Trusted Timestamping</a>. I wrote a
<a href="https://github.com/Merovius/notary">simple tool</a> as a PoC</strong></p>
<p>Recently, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/roughtime/">Cloudflare announced</a> that they are now running a
<a href="https://roughtime.googlesource.com/roughtime/">roughtime</a> server. Roughtime is a cryptographically secured
time-synchronization protocol - think NTP with signatures. For an actual
description of how it works, I recommend reading the Cloudflare blog post. But
at it&rsquo;s very core (oversimplification ahead), the user chooses an arbitrary
(usually randomly generated) nonce and the server signs it, plus the current
time.</p>
<p>One thing roughtime adds on top of this, is the ability to build a chain of
requests. This is achieved by taking a hash of a response, combining it with a
randomly generated &ldquo;blind&rdquo; and using the combined hash as a nonce to the next
request. The intended use-case of this is that if a server provides the wrong
time or otherwise misbehaves, you can obtain cryptographic proof of that fact
by getting a timestamped signature of its response from a different server. By
storing the initial nonce, generated blinds and responses, the entire chain can
be validated later.</p>
<p>When I saw Cloudflares announcement, my first thought was that it should be
possible to use a roughtime server as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trusted_timestamping#Trusted_(digital)_timestamping">Time Stamping Authority</a>. The
goal is, to obtain a cryptographic proof, that you owned a particular document
at the current point in time - for example to ensure you can proof original
authorship without publishing the document itself.</p>
<p>The simplest way to achieve this using roughtime is to use the SHA512 hash of
the file as an initial nonce. That way, the roughtime server signs that hash
together with the current time with their private key. By using the roughtime
chain protocol, you can get that proof corroborated by multiple servers.</p>
<p>You can also think of extending this, to get stronger properties. Using the
hash of the file as a nonce only proves that the file existed <em>before</em> that
specific point in time. It also doesn&rsquo;t actually prove that you had the file,
but only the hash. This can be remediated though. If we run a regular roughtime
request, the resulting response is unpredictable (to us) and signs the current
time. Thus, if we use a hash of that response as a prefix &ldquo;salt&rdquo; of the file
itself, the resulting hash proofs that we knew the file <em>after</em> that chain
ran. We can then use that hash as a nonce for another roughtime chain and get a
proof that we had the file at a specific point (or rather, a small interval) in
time. Furthermore, we can opt to use the file-hash not as the nonce itself, but
as a blind. The advantage is, that the blind is never transmitted over the
network, so the actual proof is only available to us (if we use it as a nonce,
an eavesdropper could intercept the proof). I illustrated these options in a
<a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1quTJfXHvBZCjKJgL6HjUFb_jhDF-PghBwm_lTFLAjdg/edit#slide=id.g43c753f2a5_1_542">recent talk</a> I gave on the subject.</p>
<p>These ideas are mostly academic. I&rsquo;m not sure how useful these properties are
in practice. Nevertheless, the idea intriguiged me enough to <a href="https://github.com/Merovius/notary">implement it</a>
in a simple tool. It&rsquo;s in a pretty rough, proof-of-concept like shape and I
don&rsquo;t know if I will ever progress it from there. It also comes with a client
implementation of the roughtime protocol in Go - initially I was not aware that
there already was a Go implementation, but that also is not go-gettable. Either
way, it was fun to implement it myself :)</p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">Signed blog posts</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2014-01-23-signed-blog-posts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2014/01/23/signed-blog-posts.html</id><published>2014-01-23T04:04:25+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-23T04:04:25+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>tl;dr: I sign my blog posts. curl
<a href="http://blog.merovius.de/2014/01/23/signed-blog-posts.html">http://blog.merovius.de/2014/01/23/signed-blog-posts.html</a> | gpg</strong></p>
<p><strong>Update: I no longer do this. I haven&rsquo;t for a while</strong></p>
<p>I might have to update my TLS server certificate soon, because the last change
seems to have broken the verification of <a href="https://merovius.de/">https://merovius.de/</a>. This is nothing
too exciting, but it occured to me that I should actually provide some warning
or notice in that case, so that people can be sure, that there is nothing
wrong. The easiest way to accomplish this would be a blogpost and the easiest
way to verify that the statements in that blogpost are correct would be, to
provide a signed version. So because of this (and, well, because I can) I
decided to sign all my blogposts with my gpg-key. People who know me should
have my gpg key so they can verify that I really have written everything I
claim.</p>
<p>I could have used
<a href="https://github.com/kormoc/jekyll-gpg_clearsign">jekyll-gpg_clearsign</a>, but it
does not really do the right thing in my opinion. It wraps all the HTML in a
GPG SIGNED MESSAGE block and attaches a signature. This has the advantage of
minimum overhead - you only add the signature itself plus some constant
comments of overhead. However, it makes really verifying the contents of a
blogpost pretty tedious: You would have to either manually parse the HTML in
your mind, or you would have to save it to disk and view it in your browser,
because you cannot be sure, that the HTML you get when verifying it via curl on
the commandline is the same you get in your browser. You could write a
browser-extension or something similar that looks for these blocks, but still,
the content could be tempered with (for example: Add the correctly signed page
as a comment in a tampered with page. Or try to somehow include some javascript
that changes the text after verifying…). Also, the generated HTML is not really
what I want to sign; after all I can not really attest that the HTML-generation
is really solid and trustworthy, I never read the jekyll source-code and I
don&rsquo;t want to, at every update. What I really want to sign is the stuff I wrote
myself, the markdown (or whatever) I put into the post. This has the additional
advantage, that most markdown is easily parseable by humans, so you can
actually have your gpg output the signed text and immediately read everything I
wrote.</p>
<p>So this is, what happens now. In every blogpost there is a HTML-comment
embedded, containing the original markdown I wrote for this post in compressed,
signed and ASCII-armored form. You can try it via</p>
<pre><code>curl http://blog.merovius.de/2014/01/23/signed-blog-posts.html | gpg
</code></pre>
<p>This should output some markdown to stdout and a synopsis of gpg about a valid
(possibly untrusted, if you don&rsquo;t have my gpg-key) signature on stderr. Neat!</p>
<p>The <a href="http://git.merovius.de/posts/commit/?id=dd005159f9fb25ebc8ef789608a609bcb65fc62c">changes</a>
needed in the blog-code itself where pretty minimal. I had however (since I
don&rsquo;t want my gpg secret key to be on the server) to change the deployment a
little bit. Where before a git push would trigger a hook on the remote
repository on my server that ran jekyll, now I have a local script, that wraps
a jekyll build, an rsync to the webserver-directory and a git push. gpg-agent
ensures, that I am not asked for a passphrase too often.</p>
<p>So, yeah. Crypto is cool. And the procrastinator prevailed again!</p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">New PGP Key</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2013-10-03-new-pgp-key/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2013/10/03/new-pgp-key.html</id><published>2013-10-03T00:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-10-03T00:44:00+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Because I recently applied for the position of a Debian maintainer, I
finally had to upgrade my PGP Key to a more secure 4096 bit RSA. The
new fingerprint is</p>
<pre><code>AF03 1CB8 DFFB 7DC5 E1EE  EB04 A7C9 FF06 3F3D 2E03
</code></pre>
<p>I signed the new key with my old key and <a href="http://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=vindex&amp;search=0xA7C9FF063F3D2E03">uploaded it to the
keyservers</a>.
My old key will be valid for a little longer, so you can still send me
encrypted Mails using my old key, but I would ask you to transition as
fast as possible to the new one. If the signature with my old key is
enough to earn your trust, you can delete the old key and set the new
one to trusted (and maybe even sign it again and mail me the signed
key or upload it), else you can check the fingerprint in person when
we meet next time.</p>
]]></content></entry></feed>