<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us"><generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.96.0">Hugo</generator><title type="html">in personal on Mero's Blog</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/tags/personal/"/><link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://blog.merovius.de/tags/personal/atom.xml"/><updated>2022-04-06T09:26:25+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.merovius.de/tags/personal/</id><author><name>Axel Wagner</name></author><entry><title type="html">My case for veganism</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2018-01-02-my-case-for-veganism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2018/01/02/my-case-for-veganism.html</id><published>2018-01-02T00:23:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-02T00:23:00+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m going to try to make an argument for being vegan, but, to be clear, it is
not very likely to convince you to change your eating habits. It is not
designed to - it is only supposed to change the way you think about it. I
mention all of that, so you are aware that <em>I don&rsquo;t care</em> what your conclusions
are here. If you are reading this, you should do so out of a genuine interest
of my motives and for the purpose of self-reflection - not to pick a fight with
that vegan dude and really show him he&rsquo;s wrong. I will not debate the content
of this article with you. So, with that out of the way, here is a thought
experiment:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Say, we would live in a Star Trek like post-scarcity society. Energy is all
but abundant and we figured out replicator-technology, that can instantly
create anything we like out of it. You get offer the choice between two
meals, one is a delicious steak dinner (or whatever), made in a traditional
manner. The second is the same thing, but from a replicator. Both are
indistinguishable, they taste the same, they have the same nutritional and
chemical composition, they cost the same. <em>They only differ in how they&rsquo;re
made.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You might be trying to rules-lawyer this. You might be trying to make up an
argument, for why the replicator-steak would <em>have</em> to be worse. Or that the
cow would already be dead, so it wouldn&rsquo;t matter. But that is obviously not the
point of this thought experiment (and remember, you don&rsquo;t have to convince
anyone of being right, here). The point is, that I strongly believe that the
vast majority of people would agree, that <em>all things being equal</em>, choosing
the meal that no animal suffered for is <em>the correct choice</em>. And if you truly
believe that it isn&rsquo;t, if you can honestly say to yourself that it doesn&rsquo;t
matter: You won&rsquo;t gain anything from the rest of this article. You are relieved
and might now just as well stop reading.</p>
<p>The point I am trying to make, is that you probably already know all the
reasons you <em>should</em> be vegan. It&rsquo;s very likely that you already have an
intuitive understanding of all the reasons in the &ldquo;pro veganism&rdquo; column of your
pro/contra list. And it really shouldn&rsquo;t be necessary to convince you it&rsquo;s a
good idea, in general.</p>
<p>Why then, do so few people actually <em>choose</em> to be vegan, if they are fully
aware of all the reasons to do so? The obvious answer is: Because not all
things <em>are</em> being equal. There is a &ldquo;contra veganism&rdquo; column and it&rsquo;s filled
with many good reasons <em>not</em> to. What reasons those are, is deeply individual.
It might be due to health. Due to an appeal to nature. Convenience. Money.
Availability. Taste. Or maybe just priorities: Other things seem more important
and deserving of your energy. <em>And that&rsquo;s okay</em>. We all have to make hundreds
of decisions every day and weigh these kinds of questions. And sometimes we do
things that we shouldn&rsquo;t and we usually have good reasons to. And sometimes we
compromise and don&rsquo;t go <em>all the way</em>, but just do the best we feel able to and
that&rsquo;s fine too. Nobody has to be perfect all the time.</p>
<p>The reason, I&rsquo;m writing this article anyway, is that there is a fundamental
difference between the two questions &ldquo;Why are you vegan?&rdquo; and &ldquo;Why are you not
<em>not</em> vegan?&rdquo;. When you ask me why I am vegan, you are making the conversation
inherently about my values and you will usually end up attacking them - not
because you disagree with them (you likely are not), but just because that&rsquo;s
the natural progression of this question. And to be absolutely clear: I don&rsquo;t
owe you a justification for my value system. I&rsquo;m sorry if that sounds harsh,
but the topic is mostly
<a href="/posts/2017-10-20-a-day-in-the-life-of-an-omnivore/">really annoying</a>
to me (as hard as that may be to believe at this point).</p>
<p>A more sensible question, though, is to ask how to best <em>mitigate the
contra</em>-column. If we agree that, fundamentally, the points in the pro-column
are valid and shared reasons, we can proceed into the much more productive
conversation about how much weight the downsides really have and how you might
be able to reduce at least some of their impact. And, again to be clear: The
outcome of that might very well be, that your reasons are completely valid,
rational and that, applied to your personal situation, veganism wouldn&rsquo;t be a
good choice. (And to be also clear: I might not be in the mood to have <em>this</em>
conversation either. But it&rsquo;s much preferable).</p>
<p>So, what I wish people to take away from this is</p>
<ol>
<li>Stop asking why you should be vegan (or why I am), you more than likely
already know. If you are really interested in making an informed choice,
bring up your concerns instead, but also accept if I don&rsquo;t want to talk
about them at that particular time - it&rsquo;s a lot of emotional labor, to give
the same explanations repeatedly. It might not seem like a big deal to me,
to ask these questions, but I&rsquo;ve repeated most of my answers literally
hundreds of times at this point and might prefer to just enjoy my food.</li>
<li>Stop treating veganism as a <em>preference</em> and start treating it as a <em>moral
choice</em>. There is a qualitative difference between someone who does not like
Italian food and a vegan. This is interesting when choosing what or where to
eat as a group: This is hard enough as it is and I at least usually try very
hard to accommodate everyone and not be a burden. And I absolutely do not
expect to be treated like I&rsquo;m better for that. But if it actually would come
down to a choice between a vegetarian restaurant or a steakhouse, just
because you really like meat: Yes, I do absolutely expect us to avoid the
steakhouse. (To be clear: In my experience, it rarely <em>actually</em> comes down
to only those two choices. And there are good reasons to avoid vegetarian
restaurants that are not based on preference which should be given ample
weight too - e.g. someone I know has Coeliac disease, fructose intolerance
and lactose intolerance and tends to have a very hard time eating non-meat
things. In my experience, though, people who have needs and not just
preferences tend to ironically be more open to compromise anyway, so it is
less often a problem with them).</li>
<li>Maybe think about your reasons for not being vegan and evaluate them
seriously. To be clear, this is a stretch-goal and not the actual point of
this article.</li>
</ol>
<p>And if you want to, you can watch someone who does eat meat say <em>essentially</em>
the same things here:</p>
<div class="video-container">
  <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/uwKrtNr76BM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>
<p>Thanks for reading, don&rsquo;t @ me. ;)</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="reasons-im-not-not-vegan">Reasons I&rsquo;m not <em>not</em> vegan</h2>
<p>Now, the main point of this post is dedicated to the general question of &ldquo;how I
think about the topic and how I believe you should think about it too&rdquo;. But I
also want it to serve as a reference of my personal, specific thoughts driving
my decision - so if you don&rsquo;t know me well or are not interested in my personal
reasons, this would be a good place to close the tab and do something else.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still writing this, because I hope this can be the last thing I ever have
to write about this (yeah, lol). Because again, I don&rsquo;t actually <em>like</em>
discussing it, as unbelievable as that may seem. So here is, as a reference,
why <em>I</em> am vegan (and I might add to/change this list over time, when my
viewpoints evolve). Why, after ten-ish years of thinking &ldquo;I <em>should</em> be vegan,
but…&rdquo;, I decided to make the switch - or at least give it a serious try. So,
this is a list of reasons I gave to myself to justify not going vegan and why
they stopped being convincing <em>to me</em>. Your mileage may vary.</p>
<h3 id="meatcheeseeggsbaileys-is-awesome-and-i-cant-imagine-giving-it-up">Meat/Cheese/Eggs/Bailey&rsquo;s is awesome and I can&rsquo;t imagine giving it up.</h3>
<p>For most of my life I didn&rsquo;t think about vegetarianism or veganism at all.
Eating meat was the default, so that&rsquo;s what I did. When I did start to think
about it, I convinced myself that I couldn&rsquo;t give up meat, because most of
my favorite foods where meat-based. However, a lot of people in my
peer-group around that time (university) where vegetarian or vegan, so I
naturally got into contact with a lot of good food that <em>wasn&rsquo;t</em> naturally
meat-based. So I started eating less and less meat - and the less meat I
ate, the more I realized I didn&rsquo;t really <em>miss</em> it that much, given how much
good alternatives there are. Eventually I decided to become a &ldquo;flexitarian&rdquo;,
which very quickly (in ~1-2 months) became &ldquo;vegetarian&rdquo;, when I realized
that it didn&rsquo;t actually bother me to not eat meat at all - and making that
commitment meant less decisions, so it made things easier. With
Cheese/Eggs/Bailey&rsquo;s, I basically went through exactly the same transition,
six or seven years later: &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t imagine giving them up&rdquo; - &ldquo;Actually,
there are really good alternatives&rdquo; - &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s just try reducing it and see
how far I get&rdquo; - &ldquo;Meh, might as well just commit completely&rdquo;.</p>
<p>So, to me, giving up animal products just turned out much easier, than
expected, when I actually tried. And I&rsquo;m not saying I don&rsquo;t <em>miss</em> them,
every once in a while, I will still look longingly at a steak or think
fondly of my scrambled eggs. But for the most part, the alternatives are
just as great (or at times better), so it isn&rsquo;t <em>as</em> big a sacrifice as
expected.</p>
<h3 id="being-vegetarianvegan-is-unhealthy">Being vegetarian/vegan is unhealthy.</h3>
<p>There is a bunch of research about this and for a while (especially before
actually looking into the details) the health implications of veganism
(vegetarianism not so much) did concern me. But, it turns out, this topic is
pretty complicated. Nutrition research is <em>very hard</em> - and that manifests
in the fact that for most of it, the statistical significance is usually low
and the effect sizes usually small. Now, I&rsquo;m not <em>denying</em>, that there are
health downsides to a vegan diet. But even <em>with</em> the general mess that
nutritional research is, it doesn&rsquo;t seem very controversial that if you are
concerned for your health, there are much more important factors to
consider. If weighed against the health benefits of sleeping more, doing
more sports, not sitting all day, stop recreational drug use, taking
extensive vacations… (neither of which I seem to be willing to do, even
though they would be easy enough), the relatively minor health effects of
eating animal products (contrasted with a somewhat balanced vegan diet plus
supplementation) just did not seem to be a relevant driving force for that
decision and more of a rationalization.</p>
<p>That being said, from what I can gather so far, there is a general consensus
that if a) you pay attention to having a somewhat balanced diet and b) are
willing to supplement the nutrients you <em>can&rsquo;t</em> actually get, the health
impact of veganism is pretty low, if any. Personally, I am supplementing
Vitamins B12 and D right now, which has very low quality of life impact - so
I don&rsquo;t consider that a significant downside. I also pay a little bit more
attention to what I&rsquo;m eating, which I consider a good thing.</p>
<p>If it turns out that I can not sustain a vegan diet, I will reconsider it,
but for now, I don&rsquo;t see any realistic danger of that happening.</p>
<h3 id="it-is-cumbersome-to-know-whether-or-not-something-is-vegan">It is cumbersome to know whether or not something is vegan.</h3>
<p>This is mostly true. As a vegetarian, this mostly revolved around looking
for gelatin in the ingredients of sweets and asking in a restaurant whether
&ldquo;Lasagna&rdquo; is made with meat or not. Being a vegan does involve a <em>lot</em> of
scanning ingredients-lists of basically every product I buy. Though I&rsquo;m
positively surprised how many vendors are recently starting to choose to get
their products <a href="https://www.v-label.eu/">certified</a> - and not only brands
you would expect to focus on that, but also, increasingly, all kinds of
mainstream products.</p>
<p>That being said, there <em>is</em> an availability issue (especially around &ldquo;may
contain traces of…&rdquo;, which is basically saying &ldquo;if you are allergic, we
can&rsquo;t rule out cross-contamination of other things from the same factory&rdquo;).
I tend to be pragmatic about this: If I have the choice, I will buy the
certifiably vegan option, otherwise I&rsquo;m also fine with traces of animal
products, personally. If I don&rsquo;t know, I will go with my best guess and how
I feel in the moment.</p>
<p>This is definitely the most true and heavy argument still on the contra-side
for me, but being kind of pragmatic about it helps alleviate most of the
pain.</p>
<h3 id="its-hypocritical-to-draw-the-line-at-x-and-not-at-y">It&rsquo;s hypocritical to draw the line at X and not at Y.</h3>
<p>You can always be more rigorous and there are a lot of line-drawing
questions that come up when thinking about vegetarianism/veganism. For the
record, a lot of that is just plain nonsense, but there are some
legitimate questions to be asked around whether or not insects count, for
example, or certain shellfish, whether you would eat meat if it would be
thrown away otherwise or would eat an egg, if the Hen laying it was living a
happy, free life. In the end, the vast majority of things you can eat will
involve <em>some</em> harm to the environment or animals and you won&rsquo;t always know,
so where do you draw the line?</p>
<p>Personally, I decided that <em>definite</em> harm is worse than <em>potential</em> harm
and <em>more</em> harm is worse than <em>less</em> harm. &ldquo;It is hypocritical to not eat
meat/cheese/eggs but still kill a wasp entering your apartment&rdquo; is about as
convincing an argument to me as &ldquo;it is hypocritical to eat meat/cheese/eggs
but not also eat dogs/jellyfish/human&rdquo;. The world isn&rsquo;t black-and-white and
it&rsquo;s fine to choose a gray spot in the middle that makes you comfortable.</p>
<h3 id="eating-out-becomes-a-pita">Eating out becomes a PITA.</h3>
<p>Yes. Going out and eating in a group is a PITA. Honestly, there are no two
ways about it. I do have to actively make sure that a chosen food place has
options for me and more often than not that does involve making special
requests and/or making do with less great meals.</p>
<p>In general, this still works reasonably well. The cafeteria at work has
<em>great</em> vegan options most of the time, Zurich has an amazing choice of
great restaurants for vegans to offer, most other restaurants can accommodate
too and even if not, I&rsquo;m fine just eating a little thing and then later eat
some more at home.</p>
<p>The main problem is working around the social issues associated with it -
dealing with people who are unwilling to be accommodating, having to
justify/discuss my choice or just exposing something about my person I might
prefer to keep private. Basically, I wrote
<a href="/posts/2017-10-20-a-day-in-the-life-of-an-omnivore/">a whole thing about this</a>.</p>
<p>But this is simply one of those downsides I chose to accept. Nobody said
going vegan wouldn&rsquo;t come with sacrifices.</p>
<h3 id="being-vegan-is-expensive">Being vegan is expensive</h3>
<p>I am not sure this is true <em>in general</em>. I am relatively sure, that being
vegetarian at least actually ended up <em>saving</em> me money as a student. But I
can&rsquo;t be completely certain, as the change also came with other changes in
circumstances. My vegan diet is <em>probably</em> more expensive than my vegetarian
one, mainly because it includes a lot more processed substitute products
(&ldquo;faux meat&rdquo; and various plant milks, which are at least in Switzerland
still significantly more expensive than the cow-based variants), but again,
I didn&rsquo;t actually run any numbers.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure it&rsquo;s possible to have an affordable vegan diet, especially
if limiting processed substitute products and not eating out so often.
Luckily, this isn&rsquo;t really a concern for me, right now, though. Food and
Groceries is a <em>relatively</em> small proportion of my monthly expenses and as
such, the impact this has on me is pretty limited either way.</p>
<p>I convinced myself, that if I can afford spending money on all kinds of
luxury items and electronic gadgets, I can probably afford spending a little
more on food.</p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">A day in the life of an Omnivore</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2017-10-20-a-day-in-the-life-of-an-omnivore/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2017/10/20/a-day-in-the-life-of-an-omnivore.html</id><published>2017-10-20T23:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-20T23:45:00+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You get an E-Mail. It&rsquo;s an invite to a team dinner. As you have only recently
joined this team, it&rsquo;s going to be your first. How exciting! You look forward
to get to know your new coworkers better and socialize outside the office. They
are nice and friendly people and you are sure it&rsquo;s going to be a great evening.
However, you also have a distinct feeling of anxiety and dread in you. Because
you know, the first dinner with new people also means you are going to have
the conversation again. You know it will come up, whether you want to or not.
Because you had it a thousand times - because you are an Omnivore.</p>
<p>You quickly google the place your manager suggested. &ldquo;Green&rsquo;s Organic
Foodery&rdquo;.  They don&rsquo;t have a menu on their site, but the name alone makes
clear, that meat probably isn&rsquo;t their specialty, exactly. You consider asking
for a change of restaurant, but quickly decide that you don&rsquo;t want to get a
reputation as a killjoy who forces their habits on everyone just yet. You
figure they are going to have <em>something</em> with meat on their menu. And if
not, you can always just grab a burger on your way home or throw a steak into
a pan when you get back.  You copy the event to your calendar and continue
working.</p>
<p>At six, everyone gathers to go to dinner together. It&rsquo;s not far, so you decide
to just walk. On the way you get to talk to some of your team mates. You talk
about Skiing, your home countries, your previous companies. You are having fun -
they seem to be easy-going people, you are getting along well. It&rsquo;s going to be
an enjoyable night.</p>
<p>You arrive at the restaurant and get seated. The waiter arrives with the menu
and picks up your orders for drinks. When they leave, everyone starts flipping
through the menu. “You&rsquo;ve got to try their Tofu stir-fry. It&rsquo;s amazing”, Kevin
tells you. You nod and smile and turn your attention to the booklet in your
hand. You quickly take in the symbols decorating some of the items. “G” - safe
to assume, these are the gluten-free options. There&rsquo;s also an “O” on a bunch of
them. Also familiar, but ambiguous - could be either “Omnivores&quot; or “Ovo-lacto”
(containing at least dairy products or eggs), you&rsquo;ve seen both usages. There is
no legend to help disambiguate and quickly flipping through the rest of the
menu, you find no other symbols. Ovo-lacto, then. You are going to have to
guess from the names and short descriptions alone, whether they also contain any
meat. They have lasagna, marked with an “O”. Of course that&rsquo;s probably just the
cheese but they <em>might</em> make it with actual minced beef.</p>
<p>The waiter returns and takes your orders. “The lasagna - what kind is it?”, you
ask. You are trying to avoid the O-word as long as you can. “It&rsquo;s Lasagna alla
Bolognese, house style”. Uh-oh. House style? “Is it made from cattle, or based
on gluten proteins?” (you don&rsquo;t care how awkward you have to phrase your
question, you are <em>not</em> saying the magic trigger words!) “Uhm… I&rsquo;m not sure. I
can ask in the kitchen, if you&rsquo;d like?” “That would be great, thanks”. They
leave. Jen, from across the table, smiles at you - are you imagining it, or
does it look slightly awkward? You know the next question. “Are you an
Omnivore?” “I eat meat, yes”, you say, smiling politely. Frick. Just <em>one</em>
meal, is all you wanted. But it had to come up at some point anyway, so fine.
“Wow. I&rsquo;m Ovo-lacto myself. But I couldn&rsquo;t always eat meat, I think. Is it hard?”
You notice that your respective seat neighbors have started to listen too.
Ovo-lactos aren&rsquo;t a rarity anymore (Onmivores a bit more so, but not <em>that</em>
much), but the topic still seems interesting enough to catch attention. You&rsquo;ve
seen it before. What feels like a hundred thousand times. In fact, you have
said exactly the same thing Jen just said, just a year or so ago. Before you
just decided to go Omnivore.</p>
<p>“Not really”, you start. “I found it not much harder than when I went
Ovo-lacto. You have to get used to it, of course, and pay a little more
attention, but usually you find something. Just like when you start eating
cheese and eggs.” At that moment, the waiter returns. “I spoke to the chef and
we can make the lasagna with beef, if you like”. “Yes please”, you hand the
menu back to them with a smile. “I considered going Ovo-lacto”, Mike continues
the conversation from the seat next to Jen, “but for now I just try to have
some milk every once in a while. Like, in my coffee or cereal. It&rsquo;s not that I
don&rsquo;t <em>like</em> it, there are really great dairy products. For example, this place
in the city center makes this <em>amazing</em> yogurt. But having it every day just
seems very hard“. “Sure”, you simply say. You know they mean well and you don&rsquo;t
want to offend them by not being interested; but you also heard these exact
literal words at least two dozen times. And always with ample evidence in the
room that it&rsquo;s not actually <em>that</em> hard.</p>
<p>“I don&rsquo;t really see the point”, Roy interjects from the end of the table. You
make a mental check-mark. “Shouldn&rsquo;t people just eat what they want? I don&rsquo;t
get why suddenly we all have to like meat”. It doesn&rsquo;t matter that no one
suggested that. “I mean, I do think it&rsquo;s cool if people eat meat”, someone
whose name you don&rsquo;t remember adds, “I sometimes think I should eat more eggs
myself. But it&rsquo;s just so annoying that you get these Omnivores who try to
lecture you about how unhealthy it is to not eat meat or that humans are
naturally predisposed to digest meat. I mean, you seem really relaxed about it”,
they quickly add as assurance in your direction, “but you can&rsquo;t deny that there
are also these Omni-nazis”. You sip on your water, mentally counting backwards
from 3. “You know how you find an Omnivore at a party?”, Kevin asks jokingly
from your right. “Don&rsquo;t worry, they will tell you”, Rick delivers the punchline
for him. How original.</p>
<p>”I totally get Omnivores. If they want to eat meat, that&rsquo;s great. What I don&rsquo;t
understand is this weird trend of fake-salad. Like, people get a salad, but
then they put french dressing on it, or bacon bits. I mean, if you want a
salad, why not just simply have a salad?”. You know the stupidly obvious answer
of course and you haven&rsquo;t talked in a while, so you decide to steer the
conversation into a more pleasant direction. “It&rsquo;s simple, really. You like
salad, right?” “Yeah, of course“ “So, if you like salad, but decide that you
also want to eat dairy or meat - doesn&rsquo;t it make sense to get as close to a
pure salad as you can? While still staying with your conviction to eat meat?
It&rsquo;s a tradeoff, sure, but isn&rsquo;t it better than <em>no</em> salad at all?” There&rsquo;s a
brief pause. You can tell that they haven&rsquo;t considered that before. No one has.
Which you find baffling. Every single time. “Hm. I guess I haven&rsquo;t thought
about it like that before. From that point of view it does kind of make sense.
Anyway, I still prefer the real deal”. “That&rsquo;s fine”, you say, smiling “I will
continue to eat my salad with french dressing”.</p>
<p>Your food arrives and the conversation continues for a bit, with the usual
follow-up questions - do you eat pork too, or just beef? What about dogs? Would
you consider eating monkey meat? Or Human? You explain that you don&rsquo;t worry
about the exact line, that you are not dogmatic about it and usually just
decide based on convenience and what seems obvious (and in luckily, these
questions don&rsquo;t usually need an answer in practice anyway). Someone brings up
how some of what&rsquo;s labeled as milk actually is made from almonds, because it&rsquo;s
cheaper, so you can&rsquo;t even be sure you actually get dairy. But slowly, person
by person, the topic shifts back to work, hobbies and family. “How&rsquo;s the
lasagna?”, Jen asks. “Great”, you reply with a smile, because it is.</p>
<p>On your way home, you take stock. Overall, the evening went pretty well. You
got along great with most of your coworkers and had long, fun conversations.
The food ended up delicious, even if you wish they had just properly labeled
their menu. You probably are going to have to nudge your team on future
occasions, so you go out to Omnivore-friendlier places. But you are also pretty
sure they are open to it. Who knows, you might even get them to go to a steak
house at some point. You know you are inevitably going to have the conversation
again, at some point - whether it will come up at another meal with your team
or with a new person, who you eat with for the first time. This time, at least,
it went reasonably well.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>This post is a work of fiction. ;) Names, characters, places and incidents
either are products of the author&rsquo;s imagination or are used fictitiously. Any
resemblance to actual events or locales or persons, living or dead, is entirely
coincidental.</em></p>
<p><em>Also, if we had &ldquo;the conversation&rdquo; before, you should know I still love you and
don&rsquo;t judge you :) It&rsquo;s just that I had it a thousand times :)</em></p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">I've been diagnosed with ADHD</title><link href="https://blog.merovius.de/posts/2016-08-31-ive-been-diagnosed-with-adhd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.merovius.de//2016/08/31/ive-been-diagnosed-with-adhd.html</id><published>2016-08-31T02:22:38+00:00</published><updated>2016-08-31T02:22:38+00:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>tl;dr: I&rsquo;ve been diagnosed with ADHD. I ramble incoherently for a while and I
might do some less rambling posts about it in the future.</strong></p>
<p>As the title says, I&rsquo;ve been recently diagnosed with ADHD and I thought I&rsquo;d try
to be as open about it as possible and share my personal experiences with
mental illness. That being said, I am also adding the disclaimer, that I have
no training or special knowledge about it and that the fact that I have been
<em>diagnosed</em> with ADHD does not mean I am an authoritative source on its
effects, that this diagnoses is going to stick or that my experiences in any
way generalize to other people who got the same diagnosis.</p>
<p>This will hopefully turn into a bit of a series of blog posts and I&rsquo;d like to
start it off with a general description of what lead me to look for a diagnosis
and treatment in the first place. Some of the things I am only touching on here
I might write more about in the future (see below for a non-exhaustive list).
Or not. I have not yet decided :)</p>
<hr>
<p>It is no secret (it&rsquo;s actually kind of a running gag) that I am a serious
procrastinator. I always had trouble starting on something and staying with it;
my graveyard of unfinished projects is huge. For most of my life, however, this
hasn&rsquo;t been a huge problem to me. I was reasonably successful in compensating
for it with a decent amount of intelligence (arrogant as that sounds). I never
needed any homework and never needed to learn for tests in school and even
at university I only spent very little time on both. The homework we got was
short-term enough that procrastination was not a real danger, I finished it
quickly and whenever there <em>was</em> a longer-term project to finish (such as a
seminar-talk or learning for exams) I could cram for a night and get enough of
an understanding of things to do a decent job.</p>
<p>However, that strategy did not work for either my bachelor, nor my master
thesis, which predictably lead to both turning out a lot worse than I would&rsquo;ve
wished for (I am not going to go into too much detail here). Self-organized
long-term work seemed next to impossible. This problem got <em>much</em> worse when I
started working full-time. Now almost all my work was self-organized and
long-term. Goals are set on a quarterly basis, the decision when and how and
how much to work is completely up to you. Other employers might frown at their
employees slacking off at work; where I work, it&rsquo;s almost expected. I was good
at being oncall, which is mainly reactive, short-term problem solving. But I
was (and am) completely dissatisfied with my project work. I felt that I did
not get nearly as much done as I should or as I would <em>want</em>. My projects in my
first quarter had very clear deadlines and I finished on time (I still
procrastinated, but at least at some point I sat down until I got it done. It
still meant staying at work until 2am the day before the deadline) but after
that it went downhill fast, with projects that needed to be done ASAP, but not
with a <em>deadline</em>. So I started slipping. I didn&rsquo;t finish my projects (in fact,
the ones that I didn&rsquo;t drop I am still not done with), I spent weeks doing
effectively nothing (I am not exaggerating here. I spent whole weeks not
writing a single line of code, closing a single bug or running a single
command, doing nothing but browse reddit, twitter and wasting my time in
similar ways. Yes, you can waste a week doing nothing, while sitting at your
desk), not being able to get myself to start working on anything and hating
myself for it.</p>
<p>And while I am mostly talking about work, this affected my personal life too.
Mail remains unopened, important errands don&rsquo;t get done, I am having trouble
keeping in contact with friends, because I can always write or visit them some
other time…</p>
<p>I tried (and had tried over the past years) several systems to organize myself
better, to motivate myself and to remove distractions. I was initially
determined to try to solve my problems on my own, that I did not really need
professional help. However, at some point, I realized that I won&rsquo;t be able to
fix this just by willing myself to it. I realized it in the final months of
my master thesis, but convinced myself that I <a href="https://media.licdn.com/mpr/mpr/AAEAAQAAAAAAAAJWAAAAJDIwZTMwODMwLThkZTYtNDU4Ny04ZmI3LTE3N2E2MWYxZGVlMA.jpg">don&rsquo;t have time to fix it
properly, after all, I have to write my
thesis</a>.
I then kind of forgot about it (or rather: I procrastinated it) in the
beginning of starting work, because things where going reasonably well. But it
came back to me around the start of this year. After not finishing any of my
projects in the first quarter. And after telling my coworkers and friends of my
problems and them telling me that it&rsquo;s just impostor syndrome and a distorted
view of myself (I&rsquo;ll go into why they where wrong some more later, possibly).</p>
<p>I couldn&rsquo;t help myself and I couldn&rsquo;t get effective help from my coworkers. So,
in April, I finally decided to see a Psychologist. Previously the fear of
the potential cost (or the stress of dealing with how that works with my
insurance), the perceived complexity of finding one that is both accepting
patients that are only publicly insured and is specialized on my particular
kinds of issues and the perceived lack of time prevented me from doing so.
Apart from a general doubt about its effectiveness and fear of the
implications for my self-perception and world-view, of course.</p>
<p>Luckily one of the employee-benefits at my company is free and uncomplicated
access to a Mental Health (or &ldquo;Emotional well-being&rdquo;, what a fun euphemism)
provider. It only took a single E-Mail and the meetings happen around 10 meters
away from my desk. So I started seeing a psychologist on a regular basis (on
average probably every one and a half weeks or so) and talking about my issues.
I explained and described my problems and it went about as good as I feared;
they tried to convince me that the real issue isn&rsquo;t my performance, but my
perception of it (and I concede that I still have trouble coming up with hard,
empirical evidence to present to people. Though it&rsquo;s performance review season
right now. As I haven&rsquo;t done anything of substance in the past 6 months, maybe
I will finally get that evidence…) and they tried to get me to adopt more
systems to organize myself and remove distractions. All the while, I got worse
and worse. My inability to get even the most basic things done or to
concentrate even for an hour, even for five minutes, on anything of substance,
combined with the inherent social isolation of moving to a new city and
country, lead me into deep depressive episodes.</p>
<p>Finally, when my Psychologist in a session tried to get me to write down what
was essentially an <a href="http://www.neilfiore.com/now-habit-schedules/">Unschedule</a>
(a system I knew about from reading &ldquo;The Now Habit&rdquo; myself when working at my
bachelor thesis and that I even had moderate success with; for about two
weeks), I broke down. I told them that I do not consider this a valuable use of
these sessions, that I tried systems before, that I tried <em>this particular</em>
system before and that I can find these kind of lifestyle advise on my own, in
my free time. That the reason I was coming to these sessions was to get
systematic, medical, professional help of the kind that I <em>can&rsquo;t</em> get from
books. So we agreed, at that point, to pursue a diagnosis, as a precondition
for treatment.</p>
<p>Which, basically, is where we are at now. The diagnostic process consisted of
several sessions of questions about my symptoms, my childhood and my life in
general, of filling out a couple of diagnostic surveys and having my siblings
fill them out too (in the hope that they can fill in some of the blanks in my
own memory about my childhood) and of several sessions of answering more
questions from more surveys. And two weeks ago, I officially got the diagnosis
ADHD. And the plan to attack it by a combination of therapy and medication (the
latter, in particular, is <em>really</em> hard to get from books, for some reason :) ).</p>
<p>I just finished my first day on
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methylphenidate">Methylphenidate</a> (the active
substance in Ritalin), specifically Concerta. And though this is definitely
<em>much</em> too early to actually make definitive judgments on its effects and
effectiveness, at least for this one day I was feeling really great and
actively happy. Which, coincidentally, helped me to finally start on this post,
to talk about mental health issues; a topic I&rsquo;ve been wanting to talk about
ever since I started this blog (again), but so far didn&rsquo;t really felt I could.</p>
<hr>
<p>As I said, this is hopefully the first post in a small ongoing series. I am
aware that it is long, rambling and probably contentious. It definitely won&rsquo;t get
all my points across and will change the perception some people have of me (I
can hear you thinking how all of this doesn&rsquo;t really speak &ldquo;mental illness&rdquo;,
how it seems implausible that someone with my CV would actually, objectively,
get nothing done and how I am a drama queen and shouldn&rsquo;t try to solve my
problems with dangerous medication). It&rsquo;s an intentionally broad overview of my
process and its main purpose is to &ldquo;out&rdquo; myself publicly and create starting
points for multiple, more specific, concise, interesting and convincing posts
in the future. Things I might, or might not talk about are</p>
<ul>
<li>My specific symptoms and how this has and still is influencing my life (and
how, yes, this is actual an <em>illness</em>, not just a continuous label). In
particular, there are things I wasn&rsquo;t associating with ADHD, which turn out
to be relatively tightly linked.</li>
<li>How my medication is specifically affecting me and what it does to those
symptoms. I can not overstate how <em>fascinated</em> I am with today&rsquo;s experience.
I was wearing a visibly puzzled expression all day because I couldn&rsquo;t figure
out what was happening. And then I couldn&rsquo;t stop smiling. :)</li>
<li>Possibly things about my therapy? I really don&rsquo;t know what to expect about
that, though. Therapy is kind off the long play, so it&rsquo;s much harder to
evaluate and talk about its effectiveness.</li>
<li>Why I consider us currently to be in the Middle Ages of mental health and why
I think that in a hundred years or so people will laugh at how we currently
deal with it. And possibly be horrified.</li>
<li>My over ten years (I&rsquo;m still young, mkey‽) of thinking about my own mental
health and mental health in general and my thoughts of how mental illness
interacts with identity and self-definition.</li>
<li>How much I <em>loathe</em> the term &ldquo;impostor syndrome&rdquo; and why I am (still)
convinced that I don&rsquo;t get enough done, even though I can&rsquo;t produce empirical
evidence for that and people try to convince me otherwise. And what it does
to you, to need to take the &ldquo;I suck&rdquo; side of an argument and still don&rsquo;t have
people believe you.</li>
</ul>
<p>Let me know, what you think :)</p>
]]></content></entry></feed>